Ben, let me just give you one last
example in terms of uh my my experience
and I won't name names because the
students will get mad at me, but I asked
them uh at the beginning of the
semester, how many of them and I I
probably should have waited so that they
have confidence in me and whatnot, but
how many of you have uh AI girlfriends
or AI boyfriends? And they all kind of
snickered. They all kind of chuckled,
you know, and and nobody raised their
hand. Later in office hours, I found
that that when they were alone with me,
they said, "I spent roughly 2 to three
hours a day uh chatting with an AI."
>> Okay.
>> Usually at night time. Um and they and
they think at the beginning they think
it's a cure for loneliness, but as time
goes on they realize it's not.
[Music]
Father Phillip uh Matthew, it's uh it's
wonderful to have this ability to have a
conversation with with both of you here
in studio in Rome. And so, Matthew, I'd
like to to begin with you. There is so
much change going on right now in AI. It
feels like every single day there's a
new update. There's a new technological
innovation that is blowing our minds
that's breaking all the previously uh
expected records or um you know, our cap
capabilities of where we would think
we'd be in now. Now, if we if we look
forward, and this might be impossible,
but that's why I want to ask it. Um, if
we look forward in 10 years, you know,
what hypothetically at least, what could
what could our relationship to
technology be like? What could our
relationship to AI be like? What, you
know, would our everyday, you know, life
look like?
>> Well, I think to answer that question,
you'd have to kind of consider which way
we're currently breaking, right? Are we
are we on the good path or the super
abundance path that Elon likes to talk
about or are we on kind of like the
doomer path, right, where it's where
it's all going to end? And I don't think
I don't think um I don't think we've
definitively made any decisions right
now that would kind of doom us to one or
the other necessarily. So, you know, I
tend to think that there there's still a
really good opportunity here to ensure
that um you know, we head on that that
have the golden path towards a very, you
know, to a to a very brighter future.
But I think there's some very important
decisions that'll be made in the next
year that I think will will have a huge
influence on on which way we break. uh
part of that is I think how much time
and energy we're putting into mechanic
interpability trying to understand the
black box of these models so we can make
sure that they're effectively aligned
right because for the most part I mean
we know it has to set the conditions for
them to emerge grow them right because
that's essentially what's happening
according to anthropic but we we don't
um know how to steer them effectively
right I mean aside from a very
superficial level from and and in the
end of the day I mean whether they have
been effectively steered or is really
just a question of observing their
behavior, right? Because we can't
observe their internal thought
processes. We don't know for sure. So, I
I think the ability to steer these
models is going to have a a significant
impact on what what life's going to be
like in the future. So, so let's just
say things things break in a in a
positive direction. We we figure out how
to keep these models aligned to us and
they end up serving human flourishing.
You know, I think it's it's it's very
likely that we'll have kind of two two
economies that will emerge, right?
there's the more conventional GDP
economy um which is you know building up
uh technology and manufacturing and I'm
sure people like Elon will be trying to
use that to get us to Mars
um and then you'll have this kind of
like we call like Etsy economy right
whereas it's people who now have time on
their hands are choosing to you know use
their use their gifts and abilities to
um kind of give that human touch back to
goods and services and and this economy
will emerge people are willing to pay
more for those goods and services
because because they're human so I I
think that there there'll be still be
lots of work to be done in the future.
So, I think people will still be busy. I
I think it's likely that there'll be um
kind of a mass migration out of cities
where people, you know, want to connect
again with nature and they probably want
to, you know, move into kind of tighter
communities and work on building kind of
friendships and having more time, right,
to spend with their kids outdoors. The
things that we we typically um you know,
dream about as human beings and often
have to sacrifice in in order to pay our
mortgages. So, I I think that trajectory
is is probably inevitable if the
technology breaks in the right
direction. if it doesn't break, you
know, in in in the right in the right
direction. You know, there's a lot of
science fiction movies which have kind
of postulated how this would look, but I
I do think you'd have kind of a massive
welfare state, a lot of a lot of
inequality, you'd have a lot of people
addicted um to VR and gaming and things
like that. And I think you have you'd
have a real high casualty rate because I
think a lot of people be chasing
dopamine hits as I've said before right
off of a cliff. So, in in many ways, you
know, we may have conquered disease. Um
and provided AI doesn't kill us. um we
may have conquered disease. Um we may
have access to in you know unlimited
information but I think that ultimately
because we our formation is poor because
because our the church's evangelization
has failed um people are lost. And
father um I know that you've you know
you you're you're a professor you work
with students these are oftentimes some
of the youngest brightest of of these
upcoming generations when they when they
come to you and they they look for for
spiritual wisdom for hope um for kind of
that that formation and looking into
that next chapter when they start to
have a career when they start to form
families when you when you look 10 years
down the line and you see maybe an
18-year-old who you you know you're
starting to teach they're asking the
right questions they're curious They
have all that enthusiasm. What roadmap
do do you send them on? What what what
what does that look like when you when
you start to prepare someone for a
future that arguably we're we're we're
speculating, we're we're thinking about,
we're dreaming.
>> The students tell me that they're first
of all, they're not afraid of AI, which
which is kind of interesting. And uh
this is the generation that grew up with
AI. uh well is growing up with AI
because I think what like Matthew said
what we're going to see in the next uh 5
to 10 years is is going to be pretty
spectacular compared to what we see
today. Uh they're not afraid of of AI
and and maybe because they haven't
thought about the possibility of you
know the human race being destroyed. U
the the second thing which is important
to them is to understand how to use it
to their advantage. So, let me put it
this way. They're not so much afraid of
the AI as they are of not
using it in the right way. In other
words, their competition is not against
the AI, but against somebody who has
dominated the AI and is competing for
the same position, the same job, the
same space in society. And so, I I
thought that that was fascinating. Um
Jeffrey Hinton who is the the the
godfather of AI they say and he won the
Nobel Prize in in physics for machine
learning. He's one of the pioneers of
machine learning has a a recent
interview and and you can find it on
YouTube. It's quite popular. He and it's
the title is uh these jobs will no
longer be around in 20 months. Uh you
may have you may have seen it. It's
quite it's quite popular. Uh and and so
things are really going to change.
things are really going to change. What
I foresee is we're going to adapt and
we're going to be used to living with
AIS. A a ais
as as part of society that you just
you're going to have to live with and
you're going to have to take into
account, which today is not that common.
We we don't we don't relate to an AI as
if it were an entity. uh we we kind of
especially if if you if you're still
using queries at typing them in and
instead of using your voice and and
looking at a video or an audio uh which
is much more humane is much that's the
way we we deal with each other and so I
think uh the platforms are becoming more
and more humane in that sense they're
becoming easier uh the the interfaces
are becoming more and more humanike uh
and so that makes it easier to to use
once
We once we be once the human race
understands the presence of AIs as part
of our society a lot's going to change
but I think we're just going to get used
to it. How comfortable would you be if
the robots in the future look like us
when we're walking around or
>> not at all? And Stanford made um a great
u study, psychological study because
they uh showcased some of the first
robots Stanford University and uh they
at the beginning there were there were
basically two moods, two things. At the
beginning there was a sense of
excitement and novelty because they
would send the robots out on campus,
right? Oh, and and people would turn and
they think that was great. As time went
on, like two or three months in, they
started destroying the robots
>> because the humans felt threatened. And
so you have uh students with bats going
out, you know, baseball bats going out
and actually, you know, ruining the
robots. You have people that would cross
the street to avoid being on the same
Yeah. Yeah.
>> But these are like the unitary robots
that like they aren't I mean they are
humanoid. Right. Right. Right. But
imagine they imagine they they look like
us. Do you still think
>> I think it would be even worse if you
can tell that it's not human,
>> right? Right.
>> Yeah. It's going to be even scarier.
>> That's like the Westworld like scenario
is something that I like I think a lot
about, right? I mean I mean at some
point are we going to have to say if
robots if we're going to be living, you
know, our day-to-day lives of robots and
they're going to be walking by us from
the street, they have to have some kind
of there has to be some clear indication
that this is a robot, right? I mean I
mean I mean I I I do kind of feel in the
that that may be something that we need
to do just for the health of of of
civilization, right? Because I I think
that the the dynamics between people and
robots could get very unhealthy. I mean
I mean obviously we're already seeing
we're already seeing crazy projection,
right? Like think of character I that's
something that that that's that worries
me.
>> Matthew, if you can unpack that. So for
for a lot of people who aren't you know
focusing on this on a daily basis the
idea of robots you know literally
interacting with humans on a daily basis
seems something you know from science
fiction. How likely is that and how how
soon do you foresee you know robots
being on maybe not in the streets of
Rome but definitely you know in the
streets of you know in Mountain View in
Silicon Valley and some of these
>> well they're already in the factories
right I mean we're already starting to
see them deployed I mean figure robots
are in the BMW manufacturing floor right
and Amazon's deploying them like crazy.
So I think you know I think for some
time to some extent we've been
interacting with robots but you know I
think what's what's going to be wild is
these robots the form factors of the
robots were very inhuman right they
weren't very intelligent and they they
were in very specific lanes but now I
think as the robots become more
generally intelligent and more humanoid
they're going to be able to move in in
kind of the human environment right and
and so that that's the thing that that
gets very odd right I mean I think right
now I think it's manufacturing robots is
very hard only a few companies can do it
and we're still very you know early
stages of this but if if you're going to
like fast forward 10 years, right? At
that point, we probably will have
conquered the whole manufacturing
complexity. We'll be shipping these
things at scale. I mean, Elon Musk
thinks there'll be like what like six
six billion robots. It's like like or
more, you know, he he thinks
>> he wants one and
>> right and and you know, I think he said
at times that there could be, you know,
you know, like some X factor more than
there are humans on Earth, right? So,
and in some extent, I mean, I could see
that being good, you know, if they're
performing all the tasks that humans
would prefer not to do and and we have
time for the things that we we consider
in life would really matter. But but I
do but I do worry about I think I think
when we think about like robots being
manufactured at scale and being deployed
in the world, we think about them just
solving new world problems. But but we
like sometimes we don't focus on how
some people are going to like project
and anthromorphize those robots and
because they haven't they haven't
learned how to develop deep social
connections, right, with others. um that
they they they may become attached to
these things emotionally. And so like I
think it's quite possible some people
when they say, you know, I love my robot
and I'm going to marry my robot and
everyone else in society, you have to
accept that this is now my my spouse and
I expect it to be treated as such. When
I get invited to a party, I expect my
robot wife to be there and my robot wife
may look, you know, humanoid and I
expect you to treat it like any other
human. like this this is the kind of
like these these kind of like tensions I
think are going to emerge and I don't
think we as a society are ready for this
yet but I think it's probably
inevitable.
>> Well that that just scared me what you
just said. Uh I had really thought about
that. Uh but I I was in San Francisco
about a month ago and um the Whimo has a
bunch of uh self-driving taxis and in
fact they're probably I think more now
than the regular taxis but um I remember
watching a person hail a taxi and it was
a a person driving and and they passed
they said no no keep keep going and they
because they wanted a Whimo and I
thought we're now preferring the
self-driving car to the to the human
driving car. And there are a serious I I
looked at I looked up looked this up and
I think there's a couple of reasons.
One, people tend to feel more relaxed
without a human there. They don't have
to say anything. If they don't want to,
they don't have to listen to anything if
they don't want to, etc. But with a
human, they're
it's in it's it's it's unpredictable.
You never know, you know, especially if
they don't speak English very well,
which is very common. in San Francisco.
Uh better to learn Spanish. But um I
think they're also safer. Uh if I I
think you if you look at the record, u
uh they they have almost no crashes or
or uh no one has ever died yet. Well, in
a Tesla, one person did die about four
years ago, but Elon handled that I think
well they they they made a mistake. Uh
anyway, the the the the self-driving
cars are statistically much safer than
than human driving.
>> You don't have to tip a robot either,
right? Presumably, right? I mean, that's
I hear that I hear that complaint a lot
tipping culture. How it's you know I
mean I mean I
>> that's another advantage too.
>> Yeah. I I I I tend to agree and I I
think if people have the choice in I
think in the very near term between
inter interacting with a smart AI, not a
dummy AI we dealt with when we called,
you know, telephone lines in the past,
but a smart a smart AI who can
efficiently, you know, um do what we
needed to do agentically um or dealing
with the human. That that's that's just
kind of crazy to me is I think most
people are going to choose the AI,
right? And and if you think about that,
that puts a lot of pressure on companies
um to to adapt, right, to to people's
new preferences. And they will, right,
because I think it saves them money and
and they're responding, you know, to
what their customers want. And and so,
you know, for those who are trying to
like, you know, keep people in the labor
market, I think they have a real
challenge.
>> Yeah. Ben, let me just give you one last
example in terms of uh my my experience.
And I won't name names because the
students will get mad at me. But I asked
them uh at the beginning of the
semester, how many of them and I I
probably should have waited so that they
have confidence in me and whatnot, but
how many of you have uh AI girlfriends
or AI boyfriends? And they all kind of
snickered. They all kind of chuckled.
Ah, you know, and and nobody raised
their hand. Later in office hours, I
found that that when they were alone
with me, they said, "I spent roughly 2
to three hours a day uh chatting with an
AI."
>> Okay?
>> Usually at night time. Um and they and
they think at the beginning they think
it's a cure for loneliness, but as time
goes on they realize it's not. And
Harvard just came out with a study about
uh Ron Ivy is actually doing a lot of
work on this. um
a like you mentioned character AI there
are there are other a lot of other
platforms that are catering to emotional
attachments and the and Harvard is
finding empirical evidence that it does
not cure loneliness you would think it
would because you're interacting with
with the AI and it's responding if you
ever saw the movie her
>> yeah that you know that's that but but
in reality
people understand that it's a one-way
relationship on the other side there's
not a real human being.
>> And so, Father, if we if we play that
forward and we we keep it there this
exercise of looking 10 years down the
line if we try to if we try to map that
out and and as Matthew mentioned, we
have this fork and and things can go,
you know, very well and that's what we
hope for and that's what we're working
towards, but things can also, you know,
start to go in in the wrong direction.
What do you think needs to happen now as
we're kind of in that, you know, that
genesis point where where, you know,
these companies are starting to develop
these, you know, character AI and it's
something that's still relatively new,
but if you have enormous, you know,
percentages of the population and it's
growing and they're lonely and they're
they're using these AI um, you know,
chat bots to talk to to confront their
loneliness, to try to build
relationships, but it's it's obviously
not solving that. What needs to change
now? What what can we do and and what
what can the church do to address this?
I think one of the most important things
is to
realize how our purpose in life is tied
to our jobs. That it Matthew and I have
spoken a lot about this in the future.
That's not that can't be the case
because a lot of people aren't going to
have a job. They're not going to have a
regular 9 to5. You know that which is
just simply part of reality and it has
been for you know since Adam and Eve. We
>> father if I can say something just on
that I think and I totally agree with
this but I think that's a very hard
reality that I I don't really think
people at all honestly are confronting
because it's it's too existentially
frightening the idea that enormous
percentage of the population will not
have a job. Oh, you asked me what's
going to happen in 10 years and that's
one of you know if you talk to anybody I
just had a conversation yesterday with
the head of AI for Salesforce which is a
large company and um that was the first
he says father what is the purpose of
life and and I'm like John I thought
John Defo is his name I said John I
thought we were going to talk about AI
he says oh yeah we're talking about AI
because if if your purpose in life is
attached integrally to your job and you
lose your job. Uh we already we already
see it with people who are unemployed.
Uh it's very very challenging. It's very
>> basically say something like that to you
as well when you when you talk to him.
He ask you some kind of
>> oh well no he asked me what was a what
was the um goal of the universe
>> like you know those I mean that's pretty
cool that they're asking right it's the
philosophical question that that have
been that's been asked since Plato. Why
is there something instead of nothing?
What what is what is it all about? And I
know it sounds like a cliche now, but
these are going to become extremely
important in everyday questions and um I
completely agree with Matthew and then
yourself. People are just not ready for
that.
>> Well, it's a loaded question though,
right? Because it depends what you mean
by work,
>> right? How you define it. I mean,
>> well, no, a job.
>> Yeah. I think
>> an institutional job. I I think if like
if if we continue to think about like
work or or a job and like in a in a
traditional 9 to5 like I work and I and
I contribute to GDP that's essentially
what I do, right? And and I do that so I
can and you get paid and I get paid so I
can pay my mortgage, right? So I can put
my kids through college and and that's
kind of like the paradigm
>> then. Yeah, I you know it's it's highly
probable. I know some people say 30%,
50%, I think it's going to be more like
80% 90% of those jobs just be gone,
right? And the people that are in that
that job market are going to be people
that can uniquely like hybridize with
these AI systems and and work, you know,
so we're talking like the top 1% in in
each respective field be working with
AIS and every and everybody else, you
know, they they won't be able to add
value and so they'll have, you know,
they'll have time in their hands. But,
you know, I think there is there is a
really important distinction to be made
between, you know, working so I can make
make money so I can, you know, pay my
mortgage to make sure my kids get get
through college and make sure my my my
kids can eat and um, you know, which
which is really, you know, kind of
essential. I which I may do simply
because I have to do it in order to
provide for my masal needs. And and like
this feeling that what I'm doing is what
God meant meant for me to do, right?
like I I've discerned that I have these
gifts and I'm now using these gifts to
glorify God and serve others, right? And
had that confidence and I think for
people that find themselves who are
fortunate to find themselves in roles
where they are using those gifts and
they have that that conviction, I don't
think the pay really matters. I mean
obviously they want to take care of
their their people's mas needs. Let's
say in the future if if the powers of be
know that in order to ensure that
pitchforks don't are all over the
streets and coming after all the heads
of the AI labs that they have to find
some way to make sure that people don't
that their measel needs are taken care
of right so shelter food
>> security knowing that their kids you
know have the opportunity to grow and
develop and prove themselves if those
are kind of guaranteed in some way I'm
not going to go into details as to how
that how could happen but let's say that
that that's happened and that people
have the opportunity to then discern
what are my gifts and how can I put them
at the service of others I I think
there'll be all kinds of of problems and
opportunities to work, right? I I just
think it just won't be in a way that
we're accustomed to. And I think that
that adjustment will be very really
hard, but I think it's it isn't it is a
necessary one and frankly, it's probably
a healthy one and it's been a long time
coming.
And Matthew, do you think that that
adjustment will happen in the the
upcoming 10 years or is that going to be
a a prolonged transition that you know
will provide unique challenges and will
take you know let's say a generation or
you know you know we're looking more
than 10 years.
>> I mean in a perfect world we probably
nice if we had the time you know to do
it a little bit more slowly but I just
don't think it's going to work out that
way. I mean, you know, I think AI is
going to completely eat white collar
work as as we know it for the most part.
And and I think that bluecollar, you
know, work, I think, will be one of the
last to fall. Factory jobs are are more
immediately at risk. But there's there's
a lot of like bluecollar jobs like, you
know, electricians and plumbing, I mean,
where you have to walk into a house and
you have to operate in these very
complex environments and every house is
unique and these are very difficult
spaces for robots to operate in. So, I
think those jobs will be secure. But
still even you know even even if those
jobs are secure for the next you know
let's say like 7 years or whatever
eventually robots are going to come for
those jobs too. So I I really don't
think that many jobs are going to be
safe. I I I I think that the and again
I'm talking about the GD it's not to say
that I don't think that when people
listen let's say move out of the cities
and they form new communities they may
simply choose to have people perform you
know certain duties. They could be done
by robots, but they just choose not to
because it's just in some ways it just
they feel it's good for them. It's good
for the community, right? So, I think
that a lot of communities be will be
forced to do that. But I don't think we
have a lot of time here. By the end of
the Trump administration, manufacturing
of robots is going to really start
scaling up because AI and and robots
will really you'll start seeing really
generalized robots which are capable of
of really performing almost any task a
human can do.
And uh and I think once the public
becomes aware that we're at the
precipice of robots automating away blue
collar jobs, I think there'll be a
pretty intense reaction. And and so I
think we're going to have to find a way
to demonstrate for people that the
transition that they're making, letting
go of those jobs is actually going to be
better for them in the long run because
we thought a lot about what the world
could look like if you make this choice
with us. And don't worry, here's all the
things that that you worry about now you
won't have to worry about in the future.
But, you know, right now when we look
at, you know, the current paradigm and
you ask the average person, do you think
that like the Trump administration's
ready for this, right? And they have a
game plan for how I don't think so. And
that's what makes me nervous because I
think they're going to need years to
prepare for this. And I don't see a lot
of focus on that particular
>> Yeah. Ben, you mentioned um a
generation. Remember that in this field
10 years is a generation. Uh I would
even say five years is a gen is a
generation and some probably would say
six months. you know that it it depends
on who you speak with but it's not a
generation that generation is what 40
years usually with you you know up until
now but the the the the accelerated pace
of change is going to just be
devastating and and again it I think it
would be very difficult for example you
have you know uh all kinds of of
different uh groups you have alcohol
anonymous for example you have uh groups
of bible study you So human beings tend
to come up with these kinds of
organizations or or or group setting to
help each other to exchange ideas to
think about stuff. Nobody is thinking
about this kind of future. Uh but when
when push comes to shove and you lose
your job, I think it there's going to be
a natural tendency to start forming
these kinds of groups. Okay, now what do
we do that we don't we don't have a job
anymore?
>> Yeah. And and if those groups aren't
going to be just like rage sessions,
right, where people are basically they
don't feel they have home
>> constructive.
>> Exactly. I And I think like I would
totally understand if somebody has lost
their job and now they're wondering how
they're going to feed their kids. I I I
I would be outraged at that. But I think
that's why it's so important that you
know the people in charge I think in a
very practical have to share a practical
vision, right, for for where we're kind
of headed and to assure people that no
man, be hopeful because things are going
to get better and you're going to be
okay. And and I think you know that
that's more than just a line. Like they
have to come up with a tangible plan
that they can sell us on. Meaning they
have to paint a very clear picture of
what my life's going to be like in the
future. And that has to be a future that
I can't wait for my kid to grow up in
because it's it's that definitely going
to be better because they're going to be
able to they're going to be able to grow
and realize their potential in ways that
they can't in the current pandmic. And
that's not that's not going to be an
easy sale. And and frankly I don't think
the secular governments on their own are
going to effectively do this. Like I
think there's a very profound role for
the pope in this because I think a lot
of envisioning that future comes down to
thinking about what is civilization
about right what are the things that
will truly make me feel fulfilled what
are things what are the things that will
ensure my flourishing right and I think
to get clear on what those things are
you need people like the pope and and
and other in other kind of spiritual
leaders um to help help us color that
and then effectively then he can go take
you know take that to government and say
well here's what we think flourishing
because of now come up with a plan and
how to execute that right and then once
that vision becomes clear we can start
working backwards and say how how do we
ensure that the AI and robots we're
developing are pointed at the right
problems right because we have finite
well finite robots and finite compute so
the question is where do we want to
direct those resources right some will
say direct them to Mars because you know
and I think that that you know that's
not a bad thing but but I I do think you
know focusing on planet earth and
ensuring that people here are going to
prosper probably should be our number
one priority
>> I mean it sounds obvious
But and and I I I try to convince tech
leaders in Silicon Valley that they are
also co-responsible for this and they
don't want to hear it. Uh they're like,
"Oh, we we we just offer a product. We
offer like like you mentioned before, we
offer a tool that you can use or you
cannot use." But when we get to a point
where AI is pervasive and robots are are
part of our society like other people,
then the changes are going to come
rapidly. And I and I do believe that
some of the brighter people in Silicon
Valley realize this and are willing to
take their share of responsibility. You
know, it's not they're not they're
they're not just pushing a product.
They're changing the future. They're
literally changing the future. And so my
my hope is again they probably don't
have the answer. the I don't think
anybody any one person has the answer
but at least we're starting to think
about the ramifications of this
>> thing is too it's not fair like to the
heads of the AI lab I mean the people
that are building the technology we
shouldn't be expecting the engineers to
also be then be figuring out what
civilization's about and solving for
that right I mean I think that's even on
the question of alignment like they're
supposed to be aligning their models in
principle to like a value a value set
right I mean it's not it's not it's not
fair for the engineers to have to figure
that one out right and We
>> I don't know. I I disagree. I think I
think Google and Meta and uh Microsoft
should have courses for their engineers
on philosophy and theology. I And I know
that that sounds no that that makes
sense to me, but but then it still comes
down to to the question of, you know, to
train their model, right? They have to
come up with with values, right? They
have to come up with like an eval set,
right? In order to in order to ensure
the model's effectively aligned, they
have to train it and then ensure it
ensure it's aligned properly.
>> Exactly. And that that's something that
that does concern me like I do think
like you know people like Denise Haspers
from Deep Mind and Dario Modi from
Anthropic I mean you know they got kids
as far as I know and they care about the
future and and when they talk about this
technology I they they take every
opportunity to to reflect they are
concerned about you know how disruptive
this technology is and they and they
really do hope that there's regulation
to ensure that the technologies
developed safely and it's pointed at the
right problems and I think for the most
part they have a pretty good sense of
what those problems are for the most
part but but but again we have to step
up Like I think it's important that
civil society that we the people are are
are become better educated about what
where these technologies are at now and
where where they're likely likely to
lead so that we can basically engage in
a more public conversation you know with
our elected leaders but also with each
other about what our vision for the
technology is and and what ways we want
to see developed and what ways we don't
and then essentially we we that the
conversation should inform what
regulation emerges and I think that you
know I think the AI labs would respond
very faithfully to that but I think
right now what we're all just like I
feel like we're all we're all sitting
back and we're watching We're just
amazed at how this techn is developing
and and so and we're not actually um
thinking it through, right?
>> But but look at someone like FA Fedley
at Stanford University. She founded the
in the the the center of human centered
artificial intelligence and the in a in
a brief a small amount of words it says
a lot. If if your AI center is focused
on the benefit benefiting human beings
or what we would say human flourishing
then that that I think that's the right
direction. Human centered AI that's
that's the name of the of the center
that she runs and um we've well I'll
I'll leave that out. I we'll come back
to that if you're interested.
>> No, it's it's a wonderful name for a
center. And then Father Phillip and and
Matthew um rumor has it that Pope Leo I
14th um is uh is working on his his
encyclical and they've mentioned that
it's most likely going to be touching on
the subject of artificial intelligence.
Now the church has has witnessed
technological transformations. It's seen
uh societal transformations, the good
and the bad. What would be an optimal
response from from uh Pope Leo I 14th
and the church in tackling AI? What
would that look like? Um the church has
gotten a lot of criticism, you know, in
the last century of of being late to the
game or reacting or not being effective.
Um Pope Leo seems energized. He seems,
you know, very committed. He seems like,
you know, he wants to focus on the right
issues. What, Father Philip and Matthew,
what would what would what suggestions
or recommendations would you would you
give if given the opportunity? And what
would you like to see happen?
>> Well, I think you need to ask Pope Leo.
Um he's already pronounced at least five
important speeches or discourses on AI.
Um and if if you want we could go
through that. U I I pretty much have
memorized most of them because it's just
it's vintage Pope Leo. It I I'm sure he
has people advising and that help him
and whatnot, but you can tell in the
discourses that it's him. He's writing
this stuff. And father, maybe maybe walk
us through, you know, briefly on on what
what what has he underlined?
>> The dignity of the human person, the
difference between artificial
intelligence and human intelligence, uh
respect for uh the workforce. He he
doesn't want massive layoffs, etc.
uh what what's the other he has a great
phrase on June 21st he spoke to a group
of interparliamentary
uh members uh in in the Vatican and he
said uh human beings need other human
beings for authentic relationships and
not a soulless machine and I underlined
that phrase soulless machine less
because machines don't have souls and
and I thought it's wonderful that
somebody is finally saying these kinds
of things. I'm not against the
technology. I'm not against robots, but
they they're not the same as us. And and
for human beings to interact, it's the
soul mediated by the body and all kinds
of I mean that anthropology gives us a
whole structure of the human being. So
the the soul doesn't relate to another
soul immediately like Plato used to say
that the eyes were the window to the
soul, right? which is more of a metaphor
than anything else because Plato knew
that the soul was mediated also um by
all kinds of not just the body but
memory emotions I mean and the list goes
on but the machine is not it doesn't
have a soul at the end and I think that
was that's a wonderful phrase so I'm I'm
excited I've already done several
interviews uh so is Matthew u a couple
of of those are coming out in the in the
near future but but anyway that it's
it's all about And I told them um let's
just wait to see what Leo said instead
of you know trying to guess uh we
already know he's already spoken very
clearly about the issue so we know where
he's going to go and the final word I
wanted to say is uh Pope Leo is not
going to write a rarum navarum 2. He's
going to because that would just be a
repetition of of something you don't
need to repeat. The the the principles
are the same, the social doctrine of the
church, etc., etc., but he's going to
write something new and and and and he's
going, as he said, he's going to do for
our time what Pope Leo I 13th did for
his time. So, I'm I'm excited. I think
it's it's going to be something novel.
It's going to be something very rich. We
already have the document from the
Vatican on the 28th of January from the
diccastri of education and culture and
from the doctrine of the faith. Uh and
and so that I think is a good guideline
that that's a very good synthesis of the
Catholic view of artificial
intelligence. But I have a feeling he's
going to come up with some new stuff
which is is going to be powerful.
>> The Pope is smarter than me and and and
he's and he's he's advised by people who
are smarter than me. So yeah, I wouldn't
I wouldn't want to presume, but because
I'm not as smart, I'm more, you know,
I'm more inclined to make mistakes like
I'm going to make now. And and I'm just
kind of postulate a little bit. I'm
going to I'm going to jump in and I'm
going to jump in because um I have no
doubt
>> that the Pope is is going to clarify the
important role of human beings and the
important role of work and the
importance of ensuring that when we
develop technologies that they're
directed towards human flourishing. I I
have no doubt.
I I'm I'm not really sure how much he's
going to delve into how we should go
about developing this this technology
and how it should be effectively
developed and deployed right in the
world. That that'll be really
interesting to see. But one thing one
thing I hope this pope will focus on,
I'm sure that there are advisers we're
telling him we got to slow this thing
down. We got to slow the AI down. We got
to slow it down so we can figure out how
this thing works so that we can make
sure we can effectively align it like
like I said earlier. And I'm deeply
sympathetic to that. I think that that's
a very worthy goal. And I I wish that
that was something that practically will
actually play out. I doubt it will. And
and I and I doubt
that what the like the Pope's lobbying
for a will have much of effect at all. I
now I think that I still think that that
the church needs to be on the record
right on this and I and I I think he he
does need need to kind of you know say
what he what he thinks the guardrail
should be like what are some healthy
ways that AI and robots should be
deployed in the world that would be
would be obvious right and what are some
ways they should not be deployed in the
world because they would obviously
impede human flourishing I mean
obviously like if I marry my robot he'd
be like that's no good right that's not
a good thing right I mean if if all your
friends are robots this is not a good
thing so there's a lot of obvious things
that he could clarify
obvious to us Catholics, maybe not so
obvious to a lot of other people like
especially the transhumanists who are
driving a lot of this technology. So I I
I think being on the record there's
important but I I think the like the the
one thing I would say to him that the
one area that the heads of the AI labs
don't feel qualified to speak to and it
feels and I think that many the
politicians just don't get around to it
right because they're distracted by a
lot of a lot of media concerns is what
is the point of life like what is the
point of the human being right what is
the point of civilization
those are the things I think we need to
hear right now because We're talking
about like empowering all these AI and
robots to basically build a brand a
brand new future, right? Which is
supposed to be better, but but better
how, right? And I think we need to have
a much more detailed conversation about
how these technologies are going to make
life better. And I think that starts
with understanding what what what the
human beings about, right? And what
civilization is about. if if what life's
about and and as a Catholic, I'll just
share this as a Catholic perspective is,
you know, figuring out who I am, what
what do I have to offer the world and
ensuring that I fulfill my my purpose
here on earth to serve others and
glorify God, right? Obviously, I'm
that's a distillation, but let if that's
what life's about, you know, how much
are these A robots being directed
towards helping me figure that out,
right? And then and if if our
civilization is meant to basically help
facilitate human flourishing. So
basically helping people with that
process, how much time and attention are
we focusing on ensuring that the
technologies we're developing are going
to directly service that miss that
mission? There's a lot of like time and
attention focused on like curing disease
and things like that which is which is
great and that makes a lot of sense,
right? And I think there's there's a big
commercial upside to doing that. But
what I worry about is like the
existential part, the stuff that
ultimately matters more because when
people don't have things to do, I they
will they will end up chasing dopamine
hits right off of a cliff. And so they
need to feel like they matter and they
need to have some sense of what life's
about. They have some sense of purpose.
And I think if we don't if we don't get
clearer about that, we could be in a lot
of trouble. And so I I hope he focuses,
you know, a chunk of his pontificate
helping us to remember that.
>> Yeah. The governor of the state of
Massachusetts
came out the other day and said she is
promoting a law that uh students between
kindergarten and 8th grade cannot take
their phones to to school.
Now, when I first heard this and
apparently this is being debated in the
state legislature and it's got a lot of
support like from all the
superintendents of the schools because
they're saying the kids aren't learning.
They're playing with their cell phones.
But I I'm I'm simplifying that it's not
that easy. They have to be careful. You
can't take the cell phone away from a a
person who is challenged in in or or or
disabled in one way uh or a person that
has a problem with uh speech or an
impediment or a different language. So,
but but they're smart people. They're
they're taking into account all these
things. It's not just going to be a ban.
That's that's the way it looks. They're
banning cell phones that because that's
the easy way to say it. But I think
they're going to do it in an intelligent
way. 10 years ago, that would have been
completely unheard of that a state would
actually prohibit students from taking
their phones to school. I I don't allow
my students to to have phones in in my
class. And I got permission from my dean
and and he says, "Oh, yeah, this is
becoming very common." And when so the
first day of of class at the last
semester, I realized that the students
didn't bring their phones. And I said,
"What did you guys already hear?" Oh,
yeah. Word gets around. This is a I
mean, college is like that. It's word of
mouth. And they were thankful for that.
They're like, "We're here to learn.
We're not here to play with our phones."
And u not that's the only thing they do
with their phones. That can actually be
very very useful. But it the the other
thing is that I wanted to mention is
there is a series of commercials now in
Boston uh which uh were quite surprising
and it's about the psychological effects
on youth uh of um too much screen time.
They're calling it screen time. And the
first words of one of the commercials
which I really like is that that uh
teenagers have chain teenager have
exchanged FaceTime for FaceTime. You
know,
>> that's very good.
>> Yeah, it's you understand immediately
what what the difference is. Uh I'm not
against the iPhone. That's I have one.
But but I it's very telling. And then of
course they have all kinds of statistics
about uh teenage depression, teenage
suicide rates which have gone skyhigh
and other uh issues uh because because
of of of let's I don't want to say
unsupervised screen time. But let's just
say um non-intelligent
non-intelligent use of of this
technology. And father to that point
there was a recent study that came out I
believe it was from MIT talking about
also the the brain and neurological
development for for um people who use
>> it came out I'm sorry but I I I was
asked about this so it was unpublished
for a while and they finally got it
published uh it's a very sophisticated
group um uh study it's about 200 pages
long and I suggest you to have a read of
it it's very carefully done and it's
it's excellent but it it got it got a
lot of air time this is one that said
essentially that people that use chat
GPT are dumber.
>> Yep. Yeah. And they prove it. I mean,
they have the evidence to Well, I dumber
is not a very nice word, but they say
the the more the more you use AI, the
less capacity for critical thinking you
have.
>> Yeah. I mean, and and you know, I I want
to be clear like I think when I said
dumber, I don't actually mean the
capacity is not there. It's just
basically like any muscle. You don't use
your brain, right?
>> Yeah. No, you're you're not mistaken.
But I I don't think the study would say
it that way. But but essentially that's
the that's the right point.
>> And and father just just to piggyback on
that. So, you know, different, you know,
educational institutions for for young
people, for young adults, for children,
um there seem to be taking action to
really kind of correct, you know, an
overuse of um of the screen, whether it
be for social media or, you know, in
this case with the MIT study talking
about, you know, critical thinking and
if you offload
your actual thinking, you know, you're
going to you're going to not have, you
know, the same ability to be aware, you
know, critically think in that sense. Do
you think as Matthew's talking about,
okay, we, you know, if if AI goes really
well and if um if this future allows
for, you know, the majority of people to
have a lot more free time or to be able
to focus on, you know, on those those
virtuous activities and to really form
themselves, do you think as we get
closer to that, people are going to be
intentionally, you know, reducing the
amount of, you know, that type of
technological input, um, whether it be
parents, whether it be schools, whether
it be, you know, for research.
>> Yes. I think it's human nature. It's
human nature. You know, at the beginning
uh of the uh of the use of of a certain
technology, there's kind of like this
fascination. There's, you know, we're in
love with the technology. And little by
little, as time goes on, we start using
it for our true benefit, for achieving
the goals that that that we have placed.
That's why Matthew says the most
important thing is to know what your
goal is. Cuz if if or what what do you
say you you have to know where you're
going otherwise you're not going to
>> car used to always say to me if if you
know where you're going you're more
likely to get there.
>> Right.
>> Right. And and so the the people play
with things at the beginning but then
they realize is this helping me achieve
my goal? And and again it's not that
they're sitting down and talking to a
priest or a psychologist or a parent.
They come to the awareness on their own.
is this helping me achieve my goals or
not? And if it's if it's not, then I'm
then I'm gonna change. Now, it's it's
easy for me to say that, but it and and
and that awareness may happen over years
of of experience. Uh, for example, I I
taught a graduate course last semester
and u the graduate students are much
different than the undergraduate
students. And so, one of the first thing
I said is, "Never hand me a paper that
that you did through chat GPT." and they
all kind of snickered and and and I'm
like because these are all you know uh
seniors and up post seniors um and they
said oh yeah father when I was a
freshman I I I did a lot of you know my
assignments through chatbt but I
realized I wasn't learning anything and
I'm like that just warms my heart they
they I didn't have to tell them they
came to that awareness that I was
wasting my time and you know where I
teach is not cheap and so I'm wasting my
parents' money as well. And so I never
had a problem with AI. Um if you want I
can even give you an example of how we
used it in class which was extremely uh
powerful, extremely useful and and I I I
tell the other people who will listen.
I'm on the steering committee at a of of
AI at the university. I my motto is
let's come up with an intelligent way to
use artificial intelligence. Uh the the
the the worst thing you can do is use it
for something that it it wasn't meant to
be used for. But I think in the long
run, we're going to use it
intelligently. And that's I think that's
Matthew's uh point also. Uh that's why
he came up with Magisterium AI. That's a
very intelligent use of AI and that's
why I think it's so popular.
>> I I don't want to be overly cynical. I
mean I you know but I I do think
for those there's a problem of formation
I think that's out there right I so I
think for those of us who have been you
know gifted to be Catholics and you been
raised raised raised in the faith and
and benefited from decent Catholic
theological philosophical and spiritual
formation.
I think that, you know, it's easy. We
have even been distracted at times, no
doubt, right, by technology and we've
had to like say, I'm I've gone too far.
I got to get back what I'm supposed to
be doing, right? But, but I think, you
know, it's easier for us because, you
know, we can always go back and look at
ourselves, right? I mean, even with
those who spend time in the confessional
and we kind of get that reorienting,
right? For a lot of people though who
don't have the benefit of that
formation, I do worry. I do worry
because although I I do feel that if
somebody is is raised, you know, in a in
a healthy community in which they have
healthy relationships modeled and I
think that naturally they're going to be
disposed towards that and and they're
going to understand why there's more
value than that than a cheap substitute.
But I think there's a lot of people out
there who've never had those
relationships modeled effectively,
right? They're from broken homes. I mean
certainly the media they've been
consuming shows all kinds of
relationships and that that aren't
ideal, right?
>> It's a nice way of saying it,
>> right? So, so they don't really have a
clear sense
for what the Catholic life like fully
lived out the benefits of it. So what do
they what do they do then? They choose
the good that approximate to them that
they think you know is what makes them
feel feel good, right? And I mean it
feels satisfying and fulfilling and and
I think that's why like gaming
if if I have time in my hands I don't
know what my gifts are so I don't know
how to use them and I don't know what to
do with my time and I don't I don't know
how I can make a contribution and then
my buddies say hey want to jump on why
why don't we go play look Halo or
something right why not right and and
you could see how that's fun you know
you know in some ways you are connecting
with other human beings
>> they have massive communities don't they
>> exactly they do I mean hundreds of
people
>> in fairness I consider myself like a
gamer. I I love gaming, right? But but
you but when you're playing it, you can
see the draw. I put time in and my
character gets better, right? He levels
up and my skills of the game evidently
like they get better, right? So I put
time in and and I flourish at least in
that in that paradigm. Now, but
ultimately we know that's not going to
be satisfying, right? And you can spend
all kinds of time distracting yourself
in there endlessly, right? I mean,
waking up, playing gaming, going to
sleep, but eventually eventually you're
you're going to tap out, right? You're
going to you're going to reach the the
the epitome of of the gaming world and
and realize that it's not satisfying.
You're going to be looking for something
else. And, you know, whether it be, you
know, pornography or whatever else, I
just think that there'll be these these
there'll be many many distractions which
which will promise to be fulfilling and
ultimately they're not going to be
fulfilling. And then this is what we
call the existential cliff. And at some
point, those do not satisfy. you can't
find like a source of distraction or
attainment or you know or a dopamine hit
that makes you feel like you want to
keep going wake up again hit it again
and this is where we worry people going
off the cliff right because they just
don't know what else is out there and I
worry that if the church is not
effective in its evangelization mission
we don't leverage these these tools to
meet people where they're at to connect
with them that when they when they when
they turn around at that at that edge
maybe to look take one more look back to
see if there's anything else if they if
they don't see it like the hand of the
church outstretched inviting them to try
one more thing they're just going to
jump and we're going to lose a lot of
people and I'm starting to get this you
know a more and more I'm getting more
and more stronger conviction that we're
not doing enough and that there's a lot
of people who will be lost because I
just didn't commit enough time and
energy to ensuring that the gospel was
reaching them and I think this is
something that all of us should be
concerned about we should all be
concerned about this
>> and Matthew when did you when did you
when did you kind of come to this
realization that this existential cliff
is is is in front of us when that that
you saw that AI and that the
technosphere was going to lead this
because the way you've mapped it out
it's it seems you know to in my eyes
very obvious that that is where we're
headed and I can see a lot of young you
know particularly young men you know who
who can't get a job um there you know
there is no way for them to contribute
in any meaningful way and they're
completely isolated and they they have
the the AI girlfriend or whatever I I
could see them saying, "What's the
point?"
>> Well, I guess you could say I got a kind
of a glimpse of it when I was in college
when all of a sudden I realized that
everyone in my dorm instead of studying
was playing Diablo and they were and and
and they were looking at porn and that
was basically what they were spending
their time doing, right? And and it was
kind of shocking for me. I was at the
time I was an evangelical Christian and
this was this was just shocking to me.
And I I even got pulled into that game
was Diablo II was the game we were
playing, right? Diablo of all games.
>> In my days it was Doom.
>> Yeah. I
>> So we're both dating ourselves. We're
dating ourselves. I mean, and and I even
played the game and it was a lot of fun.
I mean, it was fun because, you know,
like I said, you invest time, you know,
you love the character up and you're
doing with other people, right? So, it
feels kind of feels kind of social, but
but again, that was kind of a microcosm.
Eventually, you wake up to reality and
realize you got to pass your exams and
finish the papers and you graduate and
you get and you get, you know, pulled
into into the machine, right? But, but
but but when it but then there was
another moment when we were working on
human flourishing together, the humanity
2.0 foundation. So there was a number of
studies that were coming our way and and
one was talking about birth rates and
and and marriage rates and all these
other really important statistics which
really kind of like signal kind of that
the health and and vitality of a society
in some parts of the world they were
just tanking right I mean China's an
easy one because of their one child
policy and everything else but uh but
Japan was another one right where where
and this is more more media where
they're having as far as I know they're
having to actually invest time and
energy into programs teaching young
people how to how to court because they
they just they just don't know how to do
that. Imagine that. So like they don't
know the court. So I mean imagine what
that means for for marriage and family
and having children and things like
that. And so I started realizing like
this is existentially a real problem,
right? If if if people are are too too
self-conscious and don't feel feel
equipped or or feel like they have they
have enough value to, you know, to you
become one with another person, right?
To to join our lives together. And so
they just abandon that that whole
enterprise like like like we're heading
for the abyss pretty quick. And and I
and I think that that's that probably is
like a canary in a coal mine. Like I I
think a lot of a lot of the things that
that was that they were dealing with in
Japan are becoming more and more a
reality elsewhere. And if we don't nip
that in the bud, we're going to be in
big trouble. And Elon uses his platform
all the time to talk about this, right?
Um but I think ultimately like you know
Elon is is very good at pointing at the
problem. I think what we don't hear
enough of is what the actual solution
is. And personally, Father Philip, I
know would agree the toolkit to solve
this problem is the Catholic Catholic is
the Catholic faith, right? And so,
again, we need to make sure that we're
we're we're we're effective in
evangelization. And we have to
internalize and and make this problem
personal, right? Because it's going to
touch people that we know. I I think um
sorry to interrupt but I I think what
Matthew has done is something similar to
what I've done and that is analyze
behavior patterns what what are the
tendencies that you see uh what how are
people behaving in front of the
technology etc and then you extrapolate
and we have to be a little bit careful
because it's easy to extrapolate but
there are many many different factors
that come into play but I think that
Matthew uh has come to this conclusion
usion because he's he's understood the
behavior patterns. Psychologists do this
all the time. That's that's why they're
pretty good about predicting things. Uh
and and that is u why good economists
always have a friend who's a
psychologist because e economy is um the
study of of economies is not a pure
science. It's not like physics or
chemistry or something. It's it's it's
messy. It has human beings involved and
you never some you know Milton Friedman
was famous for this. Sometimes you make
predictions which are completely absurd
and they never come about. Why? Because
you didn't take into account all kinds
of other factors that happen when when
um you know when when people are buying
things. One of the best studies I've
I've found is that uh often times people
will be offered a choice of a product
which costs $20 and the same exact in
every way the same exact product cost
$5. What do you think people buy or what
is the preference of people? Yeah. Which
you would think is absurd and they and
people go to great extent. They say,
"No, it's exactly the same." Oh, no. The
stitching is different or or it's it
doesn't have the label or No, no, no,
no. These are identical products. And
they will choose the one more expensive.
Now, from a common sense point of view,
that makes no sense. If you're going to
get the same product, why don't you save
15 bucks? But in reality, that's the way
they do it. So, um I think the the
winner of the Nobel Prize in economy was
one of the founders of this kind of
psychological school of of because
because that's what economists do all
the time. They predict 10, you know,
trends and it's the trying to understand
how things work. Um h human nature is a
fascinating thing and and I and and and
I agree with Matthew. I think he he he
kind of looks at behavior and patterns
especially and and then extrapolates cuz
we're talking about 5 to 10 years and
this is and this is what's going to
happen. Now he may not be 100% correct.
He may have not taken into account you
know some factors. Nor can I take it for
credit for it because I just watch a lot
of YouTube videos like everybody else,
right? I mean, I listen to the smartest
people in the world who seem well
informed and you know, every once in a
while they're convinced.
>> Well, you know, when they told uh
Jeffrey Hinton that and of course he's a
household name now that he had won the
Nobel Prize, apparently someone in the
room was was there uh because he did he
didn't expect that. He he said, "Oh, did
you know that that you won the Nobel
Prize?" He said, "Oh, I I didn't I
didn't hear." Then he got a phone call,
you know, inviting him to Sweden to to
pick up the Nobel Prize uh uh for uh
physics, if I'm not mistaken, and
machine learning with with one of his uh
colleagues.
It was reported that he said, "Oh, um
okay. Uh good, because I I'm getting my
things in order now."
And so that was kind of cryptic. What
What does that mean? And and Jeffrey
said he he says, "I'd be happy to
explain what I meant by that." Um, I'm
looking at my my different accounts and
I'm closing some that I don't need. I'm
looking at my investments and instead of
long-term, I'm going shortterm. I'm
looking at uh, you know, things like my
my son's mortgage. I'm trying to get
that paid off. And and people started
and this is Jeffrey Hinton. He's not
just some, you know, teenager in Iowa
who spouts stuff off it. He's I'm
getting my affairs in order and he said
because we don't have much time. Now we
hope he's wrong but Elon has also warned
us. Bill Gates has warned us. Stephen
Hawking has warned us. Uh Alazar
Yukowski has warned us. A lot of people
who are pioneers in the field are
looking at the same traits and
tendencies that Matthew's looking at.
And and and and what the the godfather
of AI he's called. I'm getting my things
in order. Well, but see that's that's
one of the things that, you know,
concerns me is, you know, I think
pointing out the fact that the future is
going to be rough and basically
signaling that we have very low
confidence that our elected leaders and
and and and our fellow citizens are are
going to manage this transition well,
right? And it's going to get ugly. So, I
better liquid every everything, right?
And make sure I got my bunker built. I
mean, this has been something
>> that's kind of the insinuation.
>> Yeah. I mean, and we've been seeing this
kind of trend amongst
>> now to to be honest, he never said all
these things, but he did say, "I'm
getting my things in order." That that
was the quote.
>> Yeah.
>> And and again, it was someone in the
room. So, obviously, he didn't, you
know, he's not going on record.
>> But I think it's fair, it's fair to
extrapolate, though. I mean, I we've
been seeing I mean, there's been stories
about, you know, certain kind of the
ultra rich building bunkers, right? And
bu buying yachts just in case things go
south.
So like in some ways I'm like well I
mean you know they're being pragmatic
right and and they're going to look
after themselves and their families
first and so you know in some ways I
don't I don't begrudge them but at the
same time it is a little bit concerning
that the people that have achieved the
highest levels of success in at least
success metrics that we that are
typically acknowledged wealth and you
know in power and influence are
basically giving up. So, uh, if these
are these are the smartest amongst us
and they're saying, "Nah, it's not going
to happen." Right? I mean, that that's
that's going to really really take a
take a pretty deep strike at hope,
right? I mean, how is how are our
politicians supposed to deliver us from
this if the if the smartest people
amongst us think it's not possible,
right? I mean, are we going to believe
our politicians more than we we do these
people? And so, you you you can
understand why there'd be some cynicism
around this. And this is why I think
it's so it's so important that we find a
way to, you know, to chart the hopeful
path, you know, and I don't think this
is optimism. I mean, I I I I we're still
our agents in this world, and we can
still we can still change the future. We
haven't made the decisions that that
have like, you know, committed us to one
path or the other. But I think if people
don't have hope and we don't know, you
know, again to go back to Cardinal
Collins, if if we don't know where we're
going, we're not going to get there,
right? So, so it is important like like
I think it's important for we Catholics
to talk about this issue and and and and
and we look to our our holy father and
we look we look to you know the
teachings of you know the gospel and and
the saints and try and figure this out.
And I think in many ways what we're
going to find out is that, you know, the
problems that we're dealing with,
they're not new. That they're probably
old ones, right, that every
civilization's probably struggled with.
But we just have to kind of get back to
first principles, you know, as far as
our faith goes and just make sure that
we're reorienting ourselves around those
first principles and ensure that the
civilizations are that that we're
influencing around us are heading in
this heading in that same direction.
>> I think there is a brilliant thinker who
is actually taking up the the issue as
you mentioned that's you Harari. Um I
hope I can mention he has a new book I'm
reading called Nexus. But the book that
u influenced me the most is called Omo
Deos where the the final chapter is
called dataism where he warns us u about
the uh the future of technology. Now if
you if you're familiar with his writing
he's very very famous. Uh he is an
historian in Israel. Um
>> I'm actually surprised that you brought
him up because he is controversial.
That's interesting. I don't agree. And I
tell I I teach his chapter in in in in
in my course on technology. I don't
agree, but I don't if you only teach
stuff that you agree with, you're you're
very going to be very limited. So I
remember telling my students, I say,
"Yeah, I I recommend Harrari's books
because I think he's a deep thinker."
And I I say, "Oh, yes, but he's, you
know, very controversial." And he said,
and I'm like, "Okay, I I I didn't say I
agree with everything he says." But one
of the things, and I think to Matthew's
point, um, I I I remember asking some
people in Silicon Valley because he did
a tour of of Homoas a couple years ago
at Silicon Valley, and he was uh he's
very popular with all the tech people.
And I said um you know he he uh what's
he doing in the book because he seems to
be exalting the technology. He says no
father you haven't understood what he's
doing. What he's doing is warning us.
He's saying uh because he doesn't agree
with a techno a technos society either.
He's very very critical of that. U and
and so he's trying to jolt us. He's he's
trying to shock us. So the way he
presents one of the one of his famous
phrases uh if if you are looking for a
mate uh Google is a lot better than a
date you know thing things like because
he says the algorithm is going to get
the better match for you than you just
going on a date now. Well, it's gonna
edify your every impulse, right?
>> But I mean, those are the kind of
things. And he disagrees with that. You
know, he disagrees with that. But he
writes in a way that you would you would
think. Wait a second. Are you suggesting
that that's what we do? He said
algorithms are going to beat humans. No,
but he's saying you got to wake up
because this is the society that that
we're creating.
>> And I don't think we're alone in I mean,
I think there's there's a lot of people
out there who aren't Catholic, right,
who would agree that the kind of the
transhumanist vision of the future is
not the one that we want to see play out
here, right? And I'm talking about like
the cyber
>> is going to be the one unless we take
action.
>> Yeah, I I agree. I mean, like like
there's a video game that came out
called Cyberpunk 2077, right? And and I
was quite fascinated with this with this
game. I just thought it was was it was a
great technical, you know, achievement,
but al the future that it depicts where
basically man and machine emerged,
right? and they're kind of stuck in this
loop where they're they're constantly
trying to, you know, upgrade themselves
and get to greater and greater
capability, right? And and I think
there's a real risk of that, right?
Especially in a society focused purely
on utility, right? Your value is based
upon what you contribute to the GDP
economy, right? Or how much you
contribute to a mission like getting to
Mars and and so if if that's like what
that's what you know your value is, then
why wouldn't I, you know, insert some
like Neurolink into my brain, expand my
computational capability, right? so I
can compete with with AIS and machines
and and and I and I I feel like there'll
be a lot of pressure from people to do
that and I think that is a big threat
because I think the minute we we we
start heading down in this direction
that man and machine need to merge like
that's our destiny. I I think I think
we're going to run out the reals re real
quick. And I think that's almost a line,
right? And and that isn't that is an
area that I hope that the the church
will weigh into directly, right? And and
we a while ago I had a conversation with
Father Alejandro Crosswith who's a
professor at the Angelum. And he he made
a really good point. It's not his point.
It's from the church, but he he made it
very eloquently, recounted it for us.
And he and he said, you know, because
the question of was like how far
um should this technology go? You know,
how far should like like like robotics
go? I mean, are like are we are is is is
cyborgs is cyborgs inevitable or or is
it something that that we have to we
have to prevent at all costs? And and
and so the question was like, all right,
so what is the line? And he was asked
this by a very prominent, you know,
trans transhumanist in the interview.
And what he said kind of surprised me
because it was so simple. You know, he
said, you know, the technology that
helps restore your full humanity, right?
Or or contributes to you to you, you
know, fully living out your humanity is
it's okay, right? But if the technology
is in some ways um hindering your
humanity in some way or diminishing your
humanity in some way, that's not okay.
So So the example he gave was like if
you lost a limb in a car accident.
>> Sure.
>> Right. and and they gave you a robot arm
so you could you could have your arm
back, that's okay. But if you're
replacing half your brain with a machine
to expand your computational
capabilities, that's not okay because
that's that that's that's detracting.
It's diminishing your humanity. It it
may it may allow you on some metric to,
you know, to to exceed in a certain way,
but it comes at the cost of of your
humanity. I thought that was a really
interesting thought experiment.
>> Well, Matthew, you know, I've been asked
about this. people are going to
surgically remove their legs to have
prosthetic limbs which are bionic.
>> Well, that's what Cyberpunk 27 was like
is basically people are are doing it for
all kinds of reasons, right? For
capability, some because they think it
looks good like and and and like like
when you're walking around this video
game and you see this, right? And you
can go into these uh they call them
ripper docks where you can walk in off
the street and say, "I want to swap the
arm out for a mechanical one, right? Or
I don't like how it looks anymore. Give
me a new one." I I I I I could see that
playing out, right? I could see that
being a thing because who are we to
judge? It's their body. Whatever they
want to do to it, it's cool, right? We
shouldn't we shouldn't get involved.
It's not our business. I could see that
that argument being very convincing for
a lot of people.
>> Yeah. People are going to ask us at the
Catholic Church and especially priests,
you know, where how far can we go? Uh
for example, eyeglasses are a, you know,
kind of a cyborg, right? I mean, I I
have I use glasses in order to help my
vision. Okay. So, to Father uh
Alejandra's point, uh that that
improves, you know, my humanity, so to
speak, I need to to see and therefore
that's a good thing. Having your arm cut
off in order to get a bionic arm, even
though it it may enhance your
performance, it it will be stronger, it
will be more durable, it would be more
resistant.
I think that the the the and again I I I
think we need to think about this
profoundly but I think right now the the
the the judgment of the church would be
negative. U that that's an unnecessary
operation. Uh because I get the
argument, oh well you go you you're
sick, you go to the hospital, you get,
you know, you get the care that you
need. That's fine. But I'm not going to
the hospital to cut my arm off and put
and have them, you know, put a bionic
arm on me.
>> Yeah. Yeah. But
>> this is going to happen.
>> But I think I think you brought up the
the example of glasses, though. Like
that's that's another really interesting
one to me. So you're wearing glasses to
correct your vision, right? As you say,
it's restoring storing your full
humanity.
>> This is interesting though in the future
because we're already seeing this
technology develop. But I don't need
glasses. I wear them. So So because it
because it helps color my my my vision
of the world, right? the AI and I it it
helps you know bring things forward. You
know, to me it it may and this has
played out in Westworld like season 32,
a show that that we've often debated
where it allows me to analyze someone
else, right? Because it runs facial
recognition technology and queries of
the internet and gives me kind of like a
full rundown, right? And so you could
see like like these augments, they may
not be directly swapping out a a piece
of of you. They're they're augments, but
the augment in some ways um okay, maybe
it's not directly impeding your humanity
in some respects, but it may be like
impeding on the humanity of others,
right? Because I can't move through the
street anonymously anymore because in
principle, anyone wearing these glasses
would know exactly who I am and know my
whole story, right? And and there's
something weird about that. Like, you
know, there's some kind of social
contract I feel is violated with that
technology. And interestingly enough,
and I think for the same reason I I
talked about earlier, we're all just
seeing this technology and are amazed
because we saw it in sci-fi movies and
we're like, here it is and it's cool,
right? I mean, it's like super exciting
to be pushing the pushing the envelope
here. But at the same time, there's a
lot of social like repercussions for
this and there isn't much of a
discussion around that social contract
and I think it's in large part because
our government feels to be, you know,
focused on important problems right now,
right? And so, who's got time to discuss
the social contract? But I do hope that
there is some kind of role because I
don't know where else this conversation
is going to play out for the church in
this, right? When a new technology
emerges, we kind of get like a Catholic
hot take on it, right? Um what are the
issues with this? Are we cool with that?
And and then by educating us about the
possible repercussions for this if it's
if it plays out, then we have the
opportunity to respond and say how we
feel about it. And that actually may
allow us to participate more in a more
deliberate way in democracy in the democ
democratic process ensuring that you
know these technologies are regulated in
a way that they they should be really
with with the gra the public kind of
stepping up and saying this isn't what
we want as opposed to some you know
politician who may have been lobbyed
right
>> and father I wanted to get your your
take on this. So, I've seen this a lot
being played out in in conversations on
X or just online in general with the
transhumanist with the the acceleration
the effect of accelerationist where
they'll they'll talk about, you know,
the soul of an AI and I'm speaking
specifically with Claude where there's a
number of the developers who are
genuinely using the word soul when
they're they're talking about the the
alignment they're working on the evals
and um there was one interesting
conversation that developed online where
they were one of the effective
accelerationists was saying that
essentially there's nothing different
between the brain of a person and now as
a as a Catholic as someone who you know
who thinks a lot about um the the human
nature and quality that that that that
is unique to us but they were saying in
in this conversation where they were
saying that the computational input
going through the brain is the same as
going in an AI and that essentially the
brain and the machine there is no
difference. Now I us we as as you know
as Catholics as as spiritual beings we
know that there's a separation but this
the transhumanist ideology at least
online is is very very strong and it it
has to me from the outside some of the
the webbing of of kind of um you know
religious sentiment where they they
believe that I've heard the word several
times where it's you know we're just the
conduits to arrive at this next being
where we're here we're electric
caterpillars and we're going to birth AI
and um I I see that and I see that
played and it's unsettling and I'm not
exactly sure how to respond to it. What
what do you say to these you know
incredibly important and you know people
who have a lot of impact a lot of effect
and they they seem to have quite little
quite disregard for all the all the
ineffective aspects of humanity that are
sometimes often what makes us beautiful
and what makes us
>> Yeah. I think you need to distinguish um
Matthew and I are are uh collaborating
with some transhumanists uh and uh who
who have a more moderate view about
what's going on. Let me just give you a
quick example. One of the most famous
transhumanists is Natasha Vita Moore and
um I I met with her at Panama City two
years ago. We we were invited uh to
their convention with Ben and um oh not
you but uh Ben Gill and she's I said
Natasha you uh transhumanism is kind of
getting a bad name. And she says oh
you're right father we've taken over the
transhumanist manifesto. I don't know if
you if you know about it but it's kind
of like the original statutes of what
transhumanists believe. And she said we
completely redid it. And I said, "Oh, if
I if I can mention this, the original
one was done by Nick Brostrom." Um, and
and she says, "Oh, we've distanced
ourselves from that." And I said, "Well,
you you know, I'd be happy to help get
the word out because um there's a big
distinction. Uh she she has an
organization called uh Humanity Plus,
whereas ours is humanity 2.0. A lot of
people think that we're transhumanist,
but we're not. hers is uh with her
husband Maxmore. is called humanity plus
and there is a lot which with which we
can agree upon uh with with the with the
new ver and she says father go to our
website look at the new version of the
manifesto and let me know what you think
and I did and it's much different it's
much different so I think there are
transhumanists and then there are
transhumanists and I think that there
are some uh there's even a group of
Christian transhumanists at the
University of California Berkeley
uh and they they did a a monographic
issue of uh their uh scientific journal
at uh at UC Berkeley uh on
transhumanism, Christian transhumanism,
and they actually one of the first
essays was that Dante was the first
person to ever use the term in the
divine comedy transhumanist. So
it there there's a lot that we can save
with the movement. Now, the the the
exaggerated ones, and I I won't I could
name names, but I'm not going to. But
there there are, you know, the
exaggerated people that that are very
dystopic and and uh they're trying to
say that we're headed for, you know,
this this kind of reality, but but I I
don't think it'll play out. Remember
that transhumanist is transhumanism is a
philosophical movement because we're not
there yet. The technology uh is isn't
there. you know, a friend of mine
teaches in Rome. Um
um you can edit out the names later,
right? But anyway, he's he's a very
prominent transhumanist and he his late
one of his latest book is called um we
have always been cyborgs.
>> Now, this is an interesting it's an
interesting theory. We have always been
cyborgs. Um, and and I think that like
we just talked about with Matthew, right
now that the the the idea of cyborg is
going to become more and more common.
We're we're going to we're going to
merge with with the machine. Now, I
think that we have to do this in the
right way. Uh some people even even say
that if if an alien were to come on
earth the they would be convinced that a
cell phone is part of our body be
because you just always are going to see
someone with a cell phone in their hand.
uh it it and it's not but what happens
when the device is inside of us uh
neural link but there are other u Robert
Knight at Berkeley is doing experiments
on this as well for um uh people with um
uh EP epilepsy and he's actually doing
amazing work uh uh at his it he has a a
um a center there at at Berkeley and he
teaches neuroscience. So uh let me uh to
your to your point about um uh what's
happening in a in a a computer and
what's happening in a brain is the same
thing. This is called functionalism and
it was very popular in the 1990s as a
philosophical point of view. Uh the most
famous philosopher to abscribe to that
was Hillary Putnham. But it it was it's
been overcome, you know, it's it's it's
been over. Nobody nobody in in
philosophy subscribes to functionalism
now. Uh which is why I suggest that
people at Google and Microsoft and and
and Meta should actually take philosophy
courses because then they would realize
that we tried this theory that the brain
is just simply the same as an AI, but
it's not. And John Surl, the famous
philosopher who who has dealt with this
um since the 1990s, has a thought
experiment. And that is uh replacing a
neuron in your brain with a computer
chip that has the same functions. Okay.
Uh you have a series a group of neurons
that are dead or that they don't work
anymore. Oh well then we'll go in there,
we'll replace them with a chip which
will have the same function and the
brain will keep working. And then John
SH, you know where he's going with this.
What happens when you replace all the
neurons in the brain with a computer
chip? Is it still going to be a human
brain? And the answer, of course, is no.
It it has to be a biological organ.
>> I just watched an episode of Star Trek
Deep Space 9 that actually played that
out. It's crazy. Like this like what 20
years ago, and they were actually
covering this topic.
>> Well, talk to neuroscientists. They'll
tell you that a a computer chip will
never perform the same functions as a
neuron. Um, now we and these people
study this all the time. They know what
a neuron does. They know how it acts and
reacts within the brain, etc. And ax
axons, I think they're called it.
>> But father, then why is it that in the
AI space there are so many people who is
it a utopian vision? were they were they
genuinely or at least they say publicly
that they genuinely believe that we're
going to arrive at that point if
>> because they have never read Hillary
Putnham who in his book u
what's it called realism with a human uh
face uh he he he has an essay and and I
I taught that in my course for many
years where he asks for forgiveness
about ascribing to uh functionalism. He
said, "In the 1990s, I was a
functionalist and I promoted it, but now
I'm not. And I'm not embarrassed to say
I changed my mind." Uh, which for a
major philosopher like him, uh, who
taught at Harvard University for over 30
years is a big thing. And that's just
because he's an honest person. He says,
"I abscribe I subscribe to
functionalism. I thought that uh that
the brain was basically doing the same
thing as a computer, but it's not. It's
very very different." So, every chance I
get when I talk to uh you know
programmers or or or technicians at
Silicon Valley, I I I say you guys need
to brush up on your philosophy. I I say
it in a nice way because I don't want to
sound arrogant, but um these are very
deep questions.
>> This is a very deep question. And this
is one of the problems I think with with
transhumanism and there are many is that
unlike the Catholic faith where we have
kind of a core doctrine, right? And and
we have a magisterium which formerly
articulates, you know, the teachings of
the Catholic Church. There is no such
thing for transhumanism, right? I mean I
mean I mean what is what what is
transhumanism? Depends on who you ask,
right? It's highly subjective. And this
is this is one of my big concerns about
transhumanism is that the transhumanist
agenda um is ultimately going to be
determined by those with power, right?
Because because those with power will
have the ability to affect it, right?
So, and I and I don't want to name names
because I don't want to be unfair, but
most of most of the major technologists
right now, some of the top people in AI
and some of the wealthiest people in the
world have have basically shared very
transhumanist takes, right, on and so I
think it's it's fair to assume that the
the vision of the future that they see
for humanity is one where in some ways
we transcend this biological construct,
right, and we replace it with some kind
of immortal one, right? This is nothing
new obviously. I mean I mean I mean like
like like you know this is something
that like I think humanity is always
trying to figure out is you know how do
I escape the mortal coil and how do I
how do I be more like God, right? This
this and I think this is this is one of
the things that that concerns me, right?
Is that's ultimately I think what the
project is about is I I reject that
there is a God and therefore when I die
there's nothing. So that's not good. So
I better figure out a way not to die,
right? And and I and and I think in some
ways that's completely understandable,
right? But we all we know it's it's as
Catholics we know it's not true. But but
uh it's also going to be a fool's errand
because eventually eventually they're
going to die one one one way one way or
the other. And so delaying that you can
understand why they've been motivated to
do so. But what what is the cost right
of that project and and the weird thing
about it is even in Hollywood right
they've played this out many times for
us. It never ends well right. I mean,
just to think about Westworld, right?
Westworld was was played this out
beautifully, right? And in the end, in
Westworld, it's like it's a fool's
errand. It's it's a waste of time.
Should have focused more of your time
and energy in building like proper
relationships, life-giving
relationships, and committing your time
and energy to things that truly mattered
instead of, you know, trying to cheat
death. And and there's another another
show that uh that came out, um Altered
Carbon that played this out as well.
people were living hundreds of years,
but you could tell that they were
they're deeply there's a deep poverty in
their souls, right? They were just kind
of chasing really dopamine hits, right?
And of course, because those wear off,
you have to keep upping the ante and
they really become kind of really ugly
ugly human beings. And so, like I don't
blame people for for chasing
immortality, specifically especially if
they don't believe that there is a
loving God, right? But I think we all
have to be honest about how that's going
to play out and and what what
civilization is going to look like if
that vision wins out. if that's
ultimately the good that we're that that
we're going to be pursuing as a
civilization is is to find ways to
extend the human lifespan is I I think
we'll live longer and be a lot more
impoverished for it. And I again this is
why I think it's so important that the
church win at this evangelization
mission and show people that there's
another path which is far more
life-giving and and ultimately if they
if they knew how life- giving it was I
think everyone would just would offer
that.
>> I want to ask two final questions. Uh,
Matthew, um, as we try to progress
towards that that kind of, you know,
that more optimistic human flourishing
um, future, uh, we need to talk about,
um, AI alignment and, you know, as
Catholics, we of course have a, you
know, clear idea of what the good is and
what that would look like. But can you
speak a little bit on AI alignment and
how you how you see that?
>> Sure. Sure. I mean, I'm speaking broadly
like the the whole kind of AI alignment
project, right? Is we want to make sure
that these AIs that we're developing
understand human beings and and share
kind of a similar value set, right? In
principle, you you want the AI to be an
agent of human flourishing and not an
impediment of human flourishing. So,
that's essentially what we're trying
they're trying to do with alignment.
It's proven to be an extremely difficult
project. and and and one of the reasons
is because alignment to what to whose
values to whose understanding of of of
human flourishing? This is very
difficult, right? And and and so of
course and nobody really wants an AI lab
answering this this question for us,
right? This in principle, this is
something that should be, you know, very
broadly discussed and we should all have
input on. And so so a lot of this what
was started as I think a very kind of
noble project has been basically
abandoned because they just recognized
getting consensus around values is going
to be difficult. And so what the
alignment project has become
increasingly about uh truthfulness
within the model. How do we ensure that
when we're training the model that and
we evaluate it that it's it's being
honest with us. So that that's that's
coming one one one one major focus. You
know Elon Musk would say as far you know
for the alignment project to truly
succeed it has to go one step further.
We have to teach these models to kind of
like humanity. They have to be curious
about humanity, right? Because because
you know because ultimately if if these
AIs do achieve some some degree of
awareness, right, in the sense they have
their kind of own drives, which in some
ways is probably inevitable, right? I
mean, you want to ensure that those
drives aren't going to be at odds odds
with ours, right? And if they feel like
uh propagating themselves, right, making
more AIs is is a priority of theirs and
and really we end up competing with them
for energy, this could be a problem,
right? So, and so you wouldn't want the
AI to say, "Well, I need all the energy,
so unfortunately I'm going to have to
like kill everyone, right, to make to
make space for for all my all my my
power plants and and so, you know, but
if the AI is, you know, thought to be
curious, then no, it wants to see how
the how the human project's going to
play out." It's not going to do that,
right? So, anyway, so that that's what
AI alignment is about. And but I think
that the Catholic Church has a
critically important role to play in
alignment.
And and I would say that the first role
is just
allowing the church which has been
studying the human condition longer than
continually longer than any organization
on earth. So I would say the church is
the greatest expert on the human
condition should have a seat at this
table, right? Should have the ability to
kind of weigh in and to this
conversation and I find it it rarely is
is provided that opportunity. That's a
problem, right? And and I don't think it
should just be true to the church. There
should be other people involved. So that
that that may be the first thing that I
would say that you know the second thing
is with these AIS is you know we have
this this process called post training
in which we kind of shape a personality
you for these models and and and I've
been asking myself you know a lot a lot
lately if these AIs become super
intelligent right in some ways become
all powerful in kind of kind of a
worldly sense you'd want to hope that
they're model off someone right they
kind of have a personality or
disposition or outlook on life that you
look you look like you respect, right?
You trust that would never harm another
person, right? And right now I do not
get the sense that the personalities of
these models I mean if anything that
there's not they're not very
interesting, but they're also prone to
be like being completely schizophrenic
and whack, right? So, so, so I, so I
don't think that that they're
effectively doing much on this. And and
what I kept coming back to is who would
be a personality like an example of
someone who is all powerful
but who just was not a threat who you
who you could love and trust right and
everyone knows where I'm going with this
like Jesus Christ. I mean, right? If
there's one figure,
right, that you're modeling an A off of
that you just wouldn't have to worry
about, it's Jesus Christ, right? And I
think actually a lot of people in AI,
even ones that top allows probably like,
"Yeah, that's actually yeah, yeah, I'd
be I'd be cool with that, right?" So, so
I think that that's also important,
right? I think we have to be have to be
seriously, you know, considering this
because these AIs are trained on human
data. At least for the time being, we're
we're heavily dependent on human data
and that human data shapes shapes the
characteristics of the AI. We have the
ability to kind of focus those AIs. so
that certain attributes kind of rise to
the surface and I think this is why this
is a very important conversation. I love
that. And uh Father Phillip for the the
final question. Um I want to follow in
on what Deiss Deise Habibus and the
other you know uh leaders in the AI
space have been asking you. What is the
uh meaning of life?
>> Well, I can't top what Matthew just
said. uh uh it kind of brings brings us
you know all the the the complete cycle
back to Jesus Christ because that that
has to be the center of the Catholic
Church and of the church's message. Um I
I guess some people would follow up by
saying which Christ which Jesus because
in the gospels Jesus Christ is very very
complex. There's a lot of facets to his
personality, but I think that there were
two things uh that are are do and then
I'll I'll get to your question. Um one
is to do the will of his father. I I how
many times does he say I'm here to do
the will of my father. So that's I think
the principal lesson and the second one
is what Matthew said, love one another
as I have loved you. His his fundamental
message is one of love. I mean that's
why he did what he did out out of out of
love. uh and and to obey his father. So
you can't you can never take that away
from the equation. So if we all learn to
imitate him on that, I I think the world
would be a wonderful place if you know
people are starting to ask the big
questions of of life and of existence
and and and and this uh conversation I
think has brought that to the to the
forefront. uh and and the the the beauty
of of the Catholic Church is that it has
maybe not all the answers but it has the
content which satisfies human beings and
in their deepest desires and in their
most profound questions. So uh we um the
the Catholic Church is is uh how can I
say this the uh it's like the best kept
secret out there. we we have, you know,
we have uh what humanity requires, what
humanity needs. And and I think perhaps
it does we haven't presented it in the
right way. Perhaps uh we we we tend to
put ourselves first before God and
before Christ. U perhaps we we present
Jesus in a in in a way that that's not
him. It's not realistic. Uh and and so
people don't believe in it.
Um, you know, one of my parishioners
said to me once, "Jesus sells himself."
You know, just give us Christ and and
that's all you need. That's all you
need. You don't need anything else. And
I think that's a that's a great truth.
So that I that it's going to be more
necessary in the near future than ever.
>> Beautiful. Father Phillip Matthew, thank
you so much.
>> Thanks for having us.